<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Duke of Rohan peere of France, &amp;c. Containing the iustnes of reasons and motiues which haue obliged him to implore the assistance of the King of Great Britaine, and to take armes for the defence of the Reformed Churches. Translated according to the French copie.</title>
            <title>Déclaration de Monsieur le duc de Rohan, pair de France. English</title>
            <author>Rohan, Henri, duc de, 1579-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851353</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 974:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Duke of Rohan peere of France, &amp;c. Containing the iustnes of reasons and motiues which haue obliged him to implore the assistance of the King of Great Britaine, and to take armes for the defence of the Reformed Churches. Translated according to the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Déclaration de Monsieur le duc de Rohan, pair de France. English</title>
                  <author>Rohan, Henri, duc de, 1579-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Miles Flesher] for Nathanael Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Déclaration de Monsieur le duc de Rohan, pair de France.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16624:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE DVKE OF ROHAN Peere of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING THE iuſtnes of Reaſons and Motiues which haue obliged him to implore the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and to take armes for the defence of the Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated according to the French Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathanael Butter</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16624:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16624:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION of the Duke of ROHAN Peere of <hi>France, &amp;c.</hi> Containing the iuſtneſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and motiues which haue obliged him to implore the aſſiſtance of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> to take armes for the defence of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Might content my ſelfe to oppoſe the ſinceritie of all mine actions againſt the blame which igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or malicious perſons will vndertake to poure vpon mine innocencie, and vpon the neceſſitie of my reſolution: It might
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16624:3"/>
ſatisfie me if I had no regard, but to my ſelfe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to doe better, and to leaue enuy, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for a chaſtiſement to the calumniators, the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iudgement of good people, is to me in ſtead of an honourable recompence, and will alwayes giue mee more ſatisfaction then the blame of wicked people is able to doe me diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>But for as much as at the ouerture of ſo great and extraordinarie things which happen among men, euery one diſcourſeth according to his fantaſie, and oft-times euill interpretations doe ſurmount aboue the moſt ſound opinions, and that aboue all ſilence is taken for a confeſſion of the fact, and that Spirits which are facile, and eaſie to be perſwaded, if they bee not inſtructed in the truth, doe readily ſuffer themſelues to bee ſurprized, and drawne to error; from whence commeth ſuch diuerſitie of ſpeech a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, and the deuiſion of hearts torne by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie apprehenſions, alwayes accompanied with weakneſſe, and followed with ruine; and that the comming of ſtrangers into the Kingdome which men beleeue (and I doe not deny it to haue beene procured by the care of my brother, and my ſelfe,) ſhall bee for a long time the ſubiect of all the good, or of all the euill which ſhall be diſcourſed of either within or without this Kingdom: I haue thought it my duty to put to light this ſmall Diſcourſe to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie this action to all the world, to make it appeare euen vnto our enemies, that it is grounded vpon an euident right, and to our friends that wee haue beene thereunto conſtrained by the moſt powerfull lawes of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16624:3"/>It is well knowne to all men by what reaſons I was bound to conclude the peace in the treatie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Montpellier, wherein I had thought all at once to procure deliuerance, and reſpiration to the Church of God, to my King the honour and glorie which hee could deſire, and peace, and repoſe to the whole State, which was thereunto ſo abſolutely neceſſarie: to areſt the progreſſe of the King of Spaine, who outragiouſly ſpurned with his feete the beſt, and moſt faithfull Allies of this Crowne, that hee might the better come with greater facility to the end of this Monarchie, after the which hee hath long gaped; and the more eaſily to attaine this peace, wee haue yeelded our ſelues with a full confidence into his Maieſties hands, that we might be indebted for our deliuerance, next after God, to his onely goodneſſe, hauing for a precious gage of our reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, and preſeruation, his ſacred word, I was perſwaded thereunto (beſides the reaſons aboue mentioned) by the Letters of the King of Great Brittaine, and of eminent men amongſt vs, which did giue teſtimonie to haue yet much zeale for the Church.</p>
            <p>But I know not through what Councell the word which his Maieſtie confirmed vnto me all the time till hee came to Lyons, and afterwards by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny letters, was found ſo ſuddenly altered, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith violated, and all our deere, and moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary liberties oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>For in ſtead of re-eſtabliſhing according to the Acts and Conditions of the Peace of <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelier,</hi> in its firſt eſtate, the Magiſtracy is changed and parted in two by violence; a Citadell built, as a publike monument, erected to condemne or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16624:4"/>
to kill our Conſcience: and a Garriſon of foure thouſand men maintained within the Towne, to the inſupportible vexation of all the Inhabitants. In ſtead of demoliſhing the Fort of <hi>Rochell</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame promiſes ſpecified in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties acts, they haue augmented and fortifyed it with all things neceſſary for a long and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eſtabliſhment, and from the ſame doe plot many enterpriſes againſt the Towne, which being diſcouered, were authoriſed, not onely by impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but euen by recompences giuen to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers.</p>
            <p>The exerciſe of our religion is not reeſtabliſhed in the places from whence it was expelled during the warre, but even during the peace many other Churches are intangled in the ſame perſecution, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Paſtors impriſoned, Edicts and Declarations made againſt the libertie of diſcipline, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the preſence of Commiſſaries in the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Aſſemblies. And in hatred of the Religion many places are ſpoyled, and razed in time of peace, as Caumont, Caſtillon, Pont-Orſon, and others: The Chamber of the Edict (a Court of Iuſtice for thoſe of both Religions) within the Towne of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres is not reeſtabliſhed as it was promiſed, but is transferred to Beziers a ſeditious towne, and of a contrary religion. They torture, torment and ſend to the Gallies men that are innocent and of reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vpon vngrounded ſuſpitions, and inuented ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations: They diuide our Magiſtrates by a decree as at Pamies: they confiſcate the greateſt part of our goods vnder title of repriſals. To conclude, they doe all things otherwiſe then was promiſed by the treatie. I made vnto the King moſt humble, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16624:4"/>
remonſtrances by letters and deputation, but in the end they were offended with my complaints, and imputed them as a crime; the King by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe letter impoſed Silence vpon mee, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited mee any more to releeue the intereſt of our Churches, and proceeded ſo farre as to offer commiſſions to certaine neighbour Gentlemen of that place of my retreate, with great promiſes, to ſeize vpon my perſon, either aliue or dead: and for prooues of that, they haue lately ſent one to murther me, which narrowly miſſing of his purpoſe, ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Piſtoll at me burnt my Ruffe, and kild one which ſtood next behind mee, hauing before divulged among thoſe of our religion, by men wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and payed to that end, that I had ſould the libertie of our Churches, and had receiued the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable reward of their laſt infalliable deſtruction. And to couer vnto ſtrangers of our religion the deſigne which they had for our perdition, they publiſh in brute onely warre againſt the Spanyard, the league with other Princes, and States intereſſed, whilſt that vnderhand by the intermiſſion of a Legat, peace is treated with him; and finally was concluded, as the time did make it appeare, leauing for a prey vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him thoſe which they had animated, and armed out of thoſe hopes, whilſt they prepared veſſels, and all equipage neceſſary to blocke vp <hi>Rochell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The affayres were reduced to ſuch tearmes that <hi>Mountpelier</hi> was captiue, <hi>Rochell</hi> vpon the point to bee the like, all the Churches of this Kingdome threatned with bondage, and for mine owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I was cruelly vlcered to ſee my ſelfe made ſo blacke with Calumnies, as if I had by preuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation conſented to the ruine, and oppreſſion of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16624:5"/>
ſo many poore people, the complaints whereof peirced my heart, and made mee to feele a more inſupportable dolour then all the reſt of my ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Being preſſed with ſuch diſpleaſures, when all hopes of bettering our condition were taken away, and that by expreſſe letters they gaue vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the deſire of changing our condition, or to require it, ſhould bee for the time to come the greateſt, and the moſt vnpardonable of all our crimes, and that if it wee not preuented by ſome bold, and prompt reſolution, <hi>Rochell</hi> would be loſt; my brother protected the enterpriſe of <hi>Blauet,</hi> from whence inſued the precedent warre with ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, as is knowne to all men, and which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the prouidence of Almighty God, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with greater aduantage for our Churches, then wee ſhould haue hoped for: In regard that the King finding it conuenient that the peace ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded through the interuention of the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of <hi>England,</hi> who by vertue of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions bound their Maſter to the inuiolable obſeruation of the treatie, and that by writings, and an authenticall act, by them ſigned, and ſealed with their ſeales of Armes, which were in their behalfe ſent vnto vs by <hi>Monſieur de Montmartin,</hi> (at the time, when I had conuocated the Aſſembly at <hi>Niſmes,</hi> for the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the peace,) in two Originals, whereof the one is at <hi>Rochell,</hi> and the other with me, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in expreſſe tearmes as followeth: <hi>That they giue vs ſuch aſſurance, that the King of great Britaine will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by his interceſſions ioyned to our moſt humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to abridge the time for the demoliſhing of the</hi> Fort Lewis, <hi>for the which they as Ambaſſadours gaue vs all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16624:5"/>
ſuch Royall words and promiſes as we could deſire.</hi> And the ſaid Monſieur <hi>de Montmartin</hi> did aſſure mee from him in that behalfe, that they being returned into <hi>England</hi> would cauſe to bee deliuered vnto my brother another Act ſigned with the Kings owne hand, which ſhould containe in expreſſe termes, <hi>viz. That if the King ſhould refuſe, or too long deferre the razing of the ſaid Fort, and the intire obſeruation of the treaty of the peace, the ſaid King of Great Britaine would employ all the forces which God hath giuen him to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his word, and to make vs fully to inioy thoſe things which haue beene promiſed by the anſwers and declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Maieſtie, and by the act of the interuention of his Ambaſſadors.</hi> Which gaue vs hope, that either the conditions of this peace ſhould be more exactly obſerued then thoſe of the former, or in caſe of new oppreſſions, we ſhould haue for our warrant to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine vs him who made himſelfe the Mediator of the treaty, interpreter of words giuen and pledges for the inuiolable obſeruation thereof.</p>
            <p>But we haue beene ſo vnhappy, that although it ſeemed vnto vs that this peace built vpon ſo weake foundations ſhould continue many ages, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it was worſe obſerued then all thoſe which haue beene violated with more licence, and leſſe conſideration: For after that the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell had reuoked all promiſes which they had made to all ſtrangers which are allied to the Crowne, to ſigne and conclude the league againſt the Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, they made a ſhamefull peace with him, and haue equally contemned all the the Edicts which were giuen vs to moue vs to lay downe the armes wee had then taken vp for our neceſſary defence: For the Edict was not verified in the Parliaments,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16624:6"/>
but with modifications, which deſtroyed them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could we with all our ſuits euer obtaine to haue the ſaid modification to bee read: And in ſtead of razing the Fort of <hi>Rochell,</hi> and to deliuer the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment thereof from ſouldierss according to the promiſes; They haue on the contrary filled the Fort with new munitions, giuen the keeping of it to a fauorite, and multiplied the ſouldiers within the Iſles; They haue drawne and built mighty Forts, to hold them in a perpetuall ſeruitude, and to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rochell</hi> all hope of liberty for the time to come; they haue with impunity made enterprizes vpon the towne. They would exile the Paſtours which were affectionate to the conſeruation thereof; they haue filled the coaſt with ſhippes of warre, and by land they haue hindered them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gathering their fruits at Sea they haue arreſted the ſhips which brought corne for their prouiſion; They haue oppreſſed their merchandiſe with new ſubſidies, and by this meanes doe ſpoile their commerce: To conclude, they haue made them vnder the name of peace to feele the hardeſt conditions which they might ſuffer du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the calamity of the warre: and for the height of all euil, they maintaine within the incloſure of the walls Commiſſaries being armed with emiment au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who inſolently doe labour to oppreſſe the reſt of their liberties, and to ſubuert all the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their ſubſiſtance.</p>
            <p>In the meane time the generality of our Churches hath not beene more fauourably vſed; for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, who though they were alwayes promiſed, neuer came within the prouinces for the execution of the Edict; nor the exerciſe of our Religion was neuer re-eſtabliſhed in the places where it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16624:6"/>
by the declaration that it ſhould be replanted, by meanes whereof there are more then forty Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of great importance deſtitute of this conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Our Temples are by the ſame iniuſtice and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence alwaies detained from vs as they were before. And euen ſince the peace, in diuers places they haue committed new barbarous inſolencies vpon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; among others the Cardinall of <hi>Sourdis,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Peraut,</hi> all which remaine without repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and without puniſhment: And by an Edict of freſh date the 14. of Aprill, in this yeare 1627. they tearme, the liberty of our Religion, a ſimple to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, vntill (as they ſay) that we be reunited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Paſtour (that is to ſay the Pope) to make vs know that wee deceiue our ſelues in beleeuing that the moſt iuſt liberties which haue beene granted vs ſhould be perpetuall and inuiolable: And in the ſame Declaration they doe intirely ouerturne all the diſcipline of our Churches, for they doe abſolutely interdict all the Paſtours to make any politicke aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, although they bee but onely for the liberty of our conſciences, and the aſſurance which is giuen vnto vs to maintaine them: And by a like draught of the pen they blaſt all the Paſtours which are not borne within the Kingdome, taking away their liberty to come into the Eccleſiaſticall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Prouinciall or Nationall: And they prohibit vs to giue or lend Paſtours to ſtrange Churches or Vniuerſities, or to receiue any from them without expreſſe permiſſion from the King. They command them that are without, to returne without delay, and yet notwithſtanding they ſay that they may not re-enter into their houſes without Letters Patents from the King, counterſigned by a Secretary of State, and ſealed with the great Seale: To conclude they impoſe a yoak ſuch as our fathers neuer heard of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16624:7"/>The Church of <hi>Roan</hi> hauing deſired the Lord of <hi>Veilleux</hi> his Miniſter to come preach to them hee was forbidden to goe, to the end to take away for the time to come, the liberty of our Churches to prouide themſelues of Paſtours whoſe doctrine and piety ſhould be for the edification of euery one, and not to haue power to call others, but onely ſuch as ſhall be to the liking of the Miniſters of the State, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom from henceforth wee muſt addreſſe our ſelues for the like affaires, and ſo to deſtroy the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Aſſemblies and Synods, and the order hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto here maintained in our Churches. The repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of our goods are alwayes in force &amp; vertue, and if from the Chamber of the Edict ſome equitable ſentence be obtained, there is preſently found an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion by calling the matter into the Kings Counſel, or by ſome contrary iudgement of the Parliament giuen at the requeſt of a Procurator generall which doth make the former void and of none effect: And they haue condemned diuers perſons for caſes aduowed by the Generall, and aboliſhed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict; and others are burthened with great fines for the like ſubiect; and moreover there are more then 2000 warrants giuen in the Prouince of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> to take priſoners in hatred of the precedent commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which conſtraine a multitude of perſons whoſe liues are without reproach, to baniſh themſelues from their ordinary habitations, leauing their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies deſolate, to goe ſeeke their liberty, and the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their liues. The Townes which are yet left vs in diuers places, doe ſerue no more for retreats for thoſe which haue beene therein refuged in the former troubles, mine owne houſe filled with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which are driuen from their owne habitations, and expoſed to all iniuries for the ſame ſubiect. And in diuers places they haue detained in chaines, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16624:7"/>
to fines, and threatned with more grieuous puniſhment diuers perſons, for ſpeaking or writing according to our doctrine, and againſt the opinion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as at <hi>Lyons, Aix, Beziers</hi> and <hi>Montpelier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Niſmes</hi> in hatred that I had there my retreat, they haue there ſtirred vp all the perſecutions that might be imagined: They haue ſent Commiſſaries to appoint Magiſtrates contrary to the priuiledge of the place. And the Conſuls created they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted them by Decrees, and giuen out warrants for the attaching of their bodies, and neuer yet in Kings Counſell could they haue any iuſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in hatred of that which Monſieur <hi>d'Aubais</hi> had done in accepting generouſly the charge of Conſull, they haue lodged in thoſe places which belong vnto him certaine Companies of horſe to eate them vp. And was neuer any amongſt vs who either for the generall or for the particular ſince the Peace, ſuing in any requeſt to the Counſell groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Edict, hath obtained ought, but great expences, vnprofitable ſutes, continuall mockes or brauadoes, and moſt bitter temptations to bind him either through feare or hope to make ſhipwracke of his faith.</p>
            <p>I doe not here ſet downe the perſecutions which I ſuffer in mine owne particular, as ſome hauing for hire ſought my life, and remaine vnpuniſhed, and the Auocates which plead my cauſe haue beene euill intreated and ſuſpended from their charge in the Chamber at <hi>Agen:</hi> and ſtill they ſeeke by Diabolicall practices the meanes for to take away my life, whereof I dare not complaine, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to procure ſome great aduantage and honour to thoſe which make themſelues inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16624:8"/>
of ſuch cowardly &amp; diſloyall attempts: And that thoſe which haue forged the deceit by whom I was accuſed to haue made ſome enterpriſe vpon <hi>Somniers</hi> in the time of peace, who being diſcouered haue receiued no kinde of puniſhment, in ſuch ſort that the principall Officers who ſate in iudgement acknowledging mine innocencie, ſaid notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that it was important for the ſeruice of the King not to haue it manifeſted: And that my Lady my mother hauing ſought her refuge within <hi>Rochell</hi> for her ſafety, and to giue order for her affaires there, they haue vſed all poſſible meanes to haue her forth, telling the Inhabitants that ſhe was the onely obſtacle to the accompliſhment of the promiſes made vnto them for their deliuerance: And this inſtance was made after that her houſes, and my ſiſters were full of gariſons, who haue outragiouſly beaten her officers, and committed all the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable inſolencies: Which notwithſtanding are things which I would hold hidden in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, if the perſecutions which they haue made mee to ſuffer were not the reward of that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they think they owe me, for the intire affection which I haue alwayes ſincerely ſhowne for the good and for the preſeruation of all our Churches: But in this cauſe I doe not deſire that my intereſts ſhould bee had in conſideration: if I were my ſelfe alone to ſuffer all theſe miſeries, my feeling thereof ſhould neuer goe beyond the complaint: if it might ſo pleaſe Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God only for me to be caſt into the ſea ſo the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt might bee appeaſed: I ſhould alwaies bee well content to ſacrifice my goods, and my life, for the tranquilitie of the ſtate, and for the preſeruation of the Church of God, more then the which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that there is nothing which can be more deare and precious vnto me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16624:8"/>This is in Summe the matter of our griefe, whereof euery piece might ſerue for the Subiect of a very long and deplorable Hiſtory: to thoſe which ſuffer whereof notwithſtanding reſulteth that they will neither admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter mercy nor iuſtice vnto vs, nor no promiſes, nor other, no Edicts, no Declarations, nor Acts can couer vs from the perſecution which vexeth Vs, nor from greater calamities which threaten vs; neither is there any faith, how publike and eminent ſoeuer the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, for our deſtruction, is not made a glory; And it is more firmly reſolued then euer, to put in practiſe to our coſt this ſanguinarie Maxime, that there is no faith to be kept with Heretickes, for our enemies cannot loſe the deſire they haue for our perdition, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the opportunity and power ſufficient to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it, and in the concluſion, all the eſſentiall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of peace (which was thought could not be denied vs, without an euident iniuſtice, and which imploreth vengeance to God and men) are found in all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall places to be infringed and violated.</p>
            <p>And aboue all the euils ſo great and ſo ſenſible, wee haue with all conuenient humilitie powred forth our complaints and Remonſtrances at the Kings feete, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that we had endured them with a patience without example: but the practice of our enemies, and the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred which they beare vnto our Religion, haue ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ouer the iuſtnes of our Cauſe, that the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplications of our Churches both in general and particuler brought in the behalfe of a Nationall Synod, and by the generall Deputies, although formed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Order granted by our Kings, and according to the commandement and deſire of his Maieſtie, haue beene ſent away with ambiguous anſweres, or with words without effect, or with ſentences contrary to the moſt naturall iuſtice, and moſt ſolemne Edicts, the
<pb facs="tcp:16624:9"/>
power of our enemies being come to this point, that they haue call far off all hope of a generall aſſembly to draw an orderly forme of our complaints, and then haue finally prohibited our generall Deputies to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their demands in any ſuch forme, but to produce them a part piece by piece, that they might diſſipate all coniunction of our affaires, and by that meanes make our Cauſes to be particular, and ſo to hinder vs that we ſhall not bee able by any authenticall Act to verifie the body of iniuſtices, which they doe exerciſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</p>
            <p>Being taught by ſo many experiences that wee can no more hope for any iuſtice from thoſe which are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to adminiſter it, and that our ruine was irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably reſolued in the mindes of thoſe vnto whom the gouernment of the State was committed, and that our patience, in ſtead of diminiſhing our afflictions, did augment them, and made them irremediable, and that wee were in all places accuſed of too ſimple a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity or of an inſenſible ſtupiditie, in the end I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to ſeeke other courſes then thoſe which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to had beene ſo vnprofitably vſed, and more ſolid and firme meanes for our re-eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as the King of Great Brittaine was the Mediatour of the peace, and by the Act of his Ambaſſadours it was cautioned that it ſhould be inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably obſerued, I beleeued that it was not onely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but alſo moſt iuſt to haue recourſe to him, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him of the miſerable eſtate of our condition, and to let him know what care they haue taken to deceiue our facility, to delude our hopes, and to deſtroy all the apparant grounds of our liberty, to vrge the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his word, and to coniure him aſwell in my name is in the name of all our Churches, to interuent according to his promiſe, and to intercede that the
<pb facs="tcp:16624:9"/>
peace which he cauſed to be concluded might be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully executed.</p>
            <p>This is an Action which I ſuppoſe cannot bee bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med euen by our enemies, except they be without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor reproued by thoſe of our party, except they be without conſcience: For the firſt doe well know that the Lawes of neceſſity are the ſtrongeſt and moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they know as well as we our ſelues the iniuſtices which they haue done vs, the deſolations wherewith they haue threatned vs, the ſmall eſtimation of the word which was giuen vs, whereof they haue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times very audatiouſly ſaid that it was not in the Kings power to make vs to inioy it. So far forth, that the Parliaments by their vniuſt modifications haue cancelled and cut off the moſt important Articles for our ſubſiſtance; neither doe they doubt either of the reſolued deſigne ſoone or late of our perdition, and to expell vs out of the Kingdome, or of the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues which they haue made to come to the execution, in beginning with the ſubuerſion or Rochell, from the which by all kind of forces and plots they would race out the reſt of our Churches, ſo that they cannot deny but they haue reduced vs to the vttermoſt point of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, they that haue craued and borrowed the forces of ſtrangers and of a contrary Religion to their owne to oppreſſe vs, cannot iudiciouſly complaine that we haue ſought the ſuccours of our Brethren to defend vs. And which is more, our liues are in queſtion, which they plot to extinguiſh; our goods, whereof they haue violently bereft vs; our liberties, which they haue deſtroyed, and the greateſt of all, our Religion, and the conſciences which wee haue towards Almighty God, of the which they would for euer deface the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, whoſoeuer will impute it a crime vnto vs to
<pb facs="tcp:16624:10"/>
ſeeke all poſsible meanes to preſerue the poſſeſsion of things which are ſo deare and precious, is bereft of all naturall ſenſe, neither hath hee any more part of man left him but his face, and doth declare himſelfe enemy to all Religion and conſcience.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as the miniſters of the State haue thought good, that the Ambaſſadours of the King of Great Brittaine, by a moſt authenticall Act ſigned and ſealed in due forme, making themſelues, in the name of their Maſter, Mediators of the concluſion of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and obliged his authority and his word to make vs inioy the effect of all thoſe things which were promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that the Act it ſelfe was conſigned vnto vs, I cannot perſwade my ſelfe that they can be ſo farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable or paſsionate, after their conſenting to ſo ſolemne a caution as to thinke it ſtrange that wee ſhould haue our recourſe to the caution, and to the pledge which they themſelues haue choſen and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of, and that we intreat him to imploy himſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the principall party to binde himſelfe by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed wayes betweene men of this condition to performe his Royall word, to diſcharge him or his cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the ſincere and exact maintaining and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of all the things which were agreed vpon, and without the confeſsion, whereof the difference ſhould ſtill remaine, and the things ſhould be in as deplorable termes as they were before.</p>
            <p>Concerning theſe among vs which would diſapp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue this proceeding. I ſay that they cannot with a good conſcience, except therewithall they defame with odious and execrable titles the generous reſiſtance of thoſe which haue gone before vs, and who with their bloods haue atchieued vs this holy and ſafe liberty for the preſeruation whereof we doe together at this time conteſt by the ſame proceedings: which haue paſſed
<pb facs="tcp:16624:10"/>
the Sea to ſeeke the ſuccours which we haue obtained, and which went into the heart of Germanie, to raiſe multitudes of people, and to bring them into this Kingdome, and by force to binde their enemies to giue them peace and the liberty which was denyed them, and to performe the promiſe, which they had broken: And yet notwithſtanding by the Edicts of our Kings they are ſtiled faithfull and obedient Subiects and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and the memory of them ſhall euer be bleſſed in the middeſt of the Church. And beſides in that which concerneth me, it ſeemeth vnto me that all kind of right and reaſon doth authoriſe me in this purſuit, for hitherto in all our warres of Religion, I haue had in theſe parts the charge of chiefe &amp; Generall of all thoſe which in theſe Prouinces haue had their armes in their hands, for their iuſt and neceſſary defence. The firſt peace hath beene fully treated with me, according to the power which was giuen me by the generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: And in the ſecond my brother and my ſelfe alone haue ſuſtained the charge of the warre, and I haue been preſent as Generall for the defence of our Churches, and in the treaty and concluſion of peace, that cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onarie Act of the Ambaſſadors of ſtrangers was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me. And the oathes which I haue taken in all our aſſemblies doe bind mee neuer to abandon this cauſe, and to imploy all the power, vnderſtanding, and meanes which God hath giuen me for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and ſubſiſtence of our Churches both in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and in particular, and to imploy therein whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is moſt deare vnto me. In ſuch ſort that I ſhould now hold my ſelfe periured, and a forſaker of this ſo holy and ſo iuſt a Cauſe, if I ſhould not by all my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes and meanes procure the deliuerance of ſo many poore perſecuted Churches, the ordinary complaints and ſighes whereof doe interrupt my ſleepe, waken
<pb facs="tcp:16624:11"/>
my conſcience, and binde me by ſo neceſſary a duty to all that I am able to doe for the eaſing of them, I ioyne thereunto the ſtrangers Caution whereof I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for in regard that all our Churches haue receiued it with ioy and conſolation, and haue bleſſed God that the peace was concluded in that manner, they did not beleeue that it was a piece that ſhould be knawne with wormes and rotten in a coffer. But that it ſhould be dearely kept, as the authenticall gage of our ſafety, and as neceſſity ſhould binde vs to make it of value and force to our aduantage, and to oppoſe the force of them which haue taken this Cauſe in hand, againſt the violence of thoſe which might hereafter iniuſtly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe vs: and tread vnderfoot the promiſes which were giuen for our ſubſiſtance.</p>
            <p>It may ſeeme of ſome that I ſhould haue entred into communication with our Churches before I ſhould h ue reſolued for this negotiation, and to call vpon the King of Great Brittaine for his promiſe: But I doe not thinke that men of good vnderſtanding can make ſo friuolous a ſcruple. For among the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple euery one knoweth that there was no ſufficient reſolution for that, I know that all men deſired it, but I ſaw no man to at durſt attempt it, and I felt my ſelfe bound in conſcience, and authoriſed by the right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and I ſaw that we could hope for no generall aſſembly, and that all places among vs were filled with ſpies hired to diſcouer all good actions, and to make them vnprofitable, and I conſidered that to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſo tickliſh a thing to many, would be to expoſe to the winde, and to loſe that hope which was yet left vs for our re-eſtabliſhment, which is the cauſe that I choſe rather to hazard my ſelfe alone, then to neglect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of our Churches, or to expoſe any of them to the perſecution, whererein ſuch a proceeeding being
<pb facs="tcp:16624:11"/>
diſcouered, they would infallibly haue beene entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled for euer.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew that in this negotiation I haue had no other proiect then may tend to the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, I haue therein employed <hi>Monſieur de S. Blancard,</hi> whoſe zeale to the Church of God hath beene knowne to all men, whoſe integrity without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch was free from all fraud and deceipt, and who hath ſeaſoned the courage which hee hath ſhowne in all occaſions with a ſingular prudence, beyond the expectation of his age, in ſuch ſort that I hauing made vſe of a man that was ſo entirely for the publike good, and which hath ſo often expoſed his life for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the liberties which yet remained vnto our Churches, who ſo honourably ended his life in this quarrell, that the memory of him ſhall be for euer a good odour, I cannot be ſuſpected to haue done this this negotiation for any particular ambition.</p>
            <p>I will not heere ſtand to make anſwere to thoſe which ſay that what euill ſoeuer is done vs, wee ought not to repulſe it by force, notwithſtanding any right or neceſſity that may ſeeme to authoriſe our defence, but onely oppoſe thereunto a gentle patience, and a firme reſolution to martyrdome: But I leaue the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of this queſtion to diuines and Lawyers, and will onely content my ſelfe to ſay that ſuch ſpeeches in the mouthes of our enemies and of ſome of our owne are ſuggeſted by the paſſion which they haue for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And it is an effect of the hire which they haue receiued, or are made to hope for, experience ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taught vs to perceiue in many, that it is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of one that is hired, and a forerunner of a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of an Apoſtacie. For the firſt, namely our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I finde not that ſtrange, that they endeauour to lulle vs aſleepe, that they may binde vs, and put out our
<pb facs="tcp:16624:12"/>
eyes, and to impoſe the ſeruitude vpon vs which they haue proiected with leſſe perill. For they are taught by diuers proofes that our reſiſtance making them to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with vs of the feare and danger, they cannot make an attempt vpon our liues without hazarding of their owne, and it is ſafer and more eaſie for them to cut our throats in our beds, or to bring vs out of priſon to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, then to force vs in a breach or in a trench, I only wonder at their impudency, all the world know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſmall account which they make of ſuperiour powers eſtabliſhed by God, what leagues they haue made, not onely to preſerue their owne Religion and liues, but to conſtraine the Soueraigne to extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the others, not to binde him to peace, but to force him to an vniuſt and a barbarous warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his moſt affectionate ſubiects, and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; ſo farre as to diſpoſſeſſe him of his Throne, and to proteſt that they cannot ſubiect themſelues to a Prince which profeſſeth a contrary Religion to theirs. For thoſe that are among vs, I ſuppoſe that ſome ſpeake out of weaknes, and out of a deſire which they haue to ſee the ancient zeale kindled among vs, which they ſuppoſe will be extinguiſhed by the licenſe of armes: But I doe imagine alſo that many are led thereunto by falſhood and deceipt, being people little diſpoſed to doe what they ſay, and whom an hundreth crownes would make to ſpeake a very different language. As for me hauing receiued the purity of Religion from my fathers. I doe indeauour to imitate their zeale, and to follow their example, which (praiſed bee Almighty God) hath beene without reproach: I know right well that this point hath beene reſolued by excellent Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians, which bee it, in piety, be in doctrine, thoſe of this age doe not ſurpaſſe: And I beleeue that when God will deliuer vs by humane meanes, as oft times by
<pb facs="tcp:16624:12"/>
them he hath reſtored the exteriour condition of his Church, we ſhould not oppoſe our ſelues againſt this worke; but we ought to labour with the inſtruments of our deliuerance, and to acknowledge in this, aboue all the bleſsings of God powred vpon the Saints, and vpon the generous labours of our anceſtours, that by their firme and bold reſiſtance, it hath pleaſed the Lord to procure libertie, reſt, and proſperity to his Church.</p>
            <p>Therefore the publike neceſsity being ſtronger then our patience which by little and little made it ſelfe guilty of our deſtruction, we had our recourſe to the King of Great Britaine to obtaine, either by his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion or by his power that the Edicts made for our ſubſiſtance might be obſerued, and that the promiſe which was giuen vs, wherein, his, alſo was ingaged for our libertie, might not be violated: and that my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his preſence and his continuall ſolicitations, had greatly aduanced it, Almighty God hath giuen me the grace to bring it to perfection, by the imployment of <hi>Monſieur de S. Blancard.</hi> For the King of Great Britaine moued with a feruent zeale for the defence of the Chriſtian faith, and with an inceſſant deſire to ſee the Church of God out of oppreſsion throughout all parts of the earth, there being no place, where ſince the ſmall time that God hath called him to the conduct of his Kingdomes that this affection hath not borne his courage, and imployed his forces, hath imbraced this Cauſe with great vigour, not moued thereunto out of any ambitious deſire to intrude vpon others, but onely out of the compaſsion, which hee hath of our miſeries, and the diſpleaſure to ſee his interuention with ſo great indignity contemned, ſo farre forth as that they will make it ſerue for the oppreſsion of thoſe whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to releeue; and thereby to adde vnto his Crowne that rich flowre of honour, to bee the deliuerer of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:16624:13"/>
of this Kingdome, which by their faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie euen in the perſecutions haue made themſelues to be celebrate throughout the world.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, hee hath let vs know that to bee his onely deſigne, to the which hee proteſteth to betake himſelfe with ſo great firmneſſe, as it hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly confirmed vnto me by men of quality, which hee hath done mee the honour to ſend vnto mee, that hee would neuer let goe his hold vntill ſuch time as that it ſhould plainely appeare vnto him, that by an intire aſſurance he hath atchieued vs a firme repoſe, and a ſolid contentment: requiring of vs nothing elſe but that which the Churches which are in the eſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, I ſhould doe my duety, not onely to approue the requeſt which the ſaid <hi>Seignieur de S. Blancard</hi> had made vnto him in my behalfe, in the name of our Churches; but alſo to ioyne our ſelues vnto his armes, and not to deport our ſelues from the generall end, for the reſpect of any particular accommodation, and ioyntly with him to obtaine a good, firme, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red peace, which ſhall reſtore vnto all our Churches, at the leaſt part of the proſperity from the which they are fallen.</p>
            <p>And this is the cauſe wherefore in the name of God I doe ſummon thoſe which haue any remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ancient zeale in their hearts, and which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue ſighed, in attending who ſhould come from any part for the deliuerance of the Church of God, and which haue alwayes proteſted, that when they ſhould ſee any aſſured grounds of reſiſtance or of ſubſiſtance, they would make it appeare that they had no leſſe affection then the reſt for the conſolation of ſo many poore perſecuted flocks, nor ſhow no leſſe reſolution to ſacrifice all they haue to ſo holy and ſo glorious an enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16624:13"/>Therefore the Cauſe now in hand cannot be ſaid to be vniuſt; for there was neuer any more needfull: nor the reſolution to enter thereinto raſh, hauing for our protector a Prince ſo religious, ſo faithfull, ſo neare a neighbour, and ſo powerfull: neither is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne impatient, in regard that for the ſpace of a whole yeare, wee haue to ſmall purpoſe expected to ſee the perſecution to ceaſe, and the promiſed things to bee obſerued: nor the execution of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne criminall, foraſmuch as wee haue no other end but the reſtitution of the Churches by the means here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore vſed by our Fathers, fauoured of God, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed by naturall and politicke right.</p>
            <p>As for mee, I ſhould for euer feele my conſcience charged before God, and mine honour defaced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, if hauing ſeene ſo many oppreſsions vpon the Church, for the which the Sonne of God hath ſhed his blood and indured death; I ſhould not ſeeke with all my power and meanes to eaſe it, and ſeeing ſo great a day of deliuerance to offer it ſelfe vnto mee, if I ſhould not follow and embrace ſo opportune a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, which wee may iuſtly ſay to bee ſent vs from aboue; and if I had either through conſideration or through delayes of ſlothfulneſſe diuerted ſo great a bleſsing, and refuſed an occaſion ſo aduantagious to draw vs from the ſhame and miſerie wherein wee are: confeſsing freely that I can no longer liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many publike calamities no more then I can ſuruiue after the full diſsipation of the Church, wherewith wee ſee our ſelues ſo nearely threatned: alſo I beleeue that all thoſe which hitherto God hath preſerued by ſo many of his powerfull maruailes, will not bee ſlacke to ſo laudable a worke, and I haue too good an opinion of the courage and zeale of euery one, to thinke that they would withdraw
<pb facs="tcp:16624:14"/>
themſelues through impiety, or to deſtroy it through perfidiouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>And I aſſure my ſelfe, that time ſhall make all men to ſee, that I haue not beene moued to this enterpriſe out of any deſire to make my ſelfe great, or to make any profit of the publike ruine: For at the ſame time I ſee my ſelfe engaged to trauailes, diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, and continuall watchings, to bee inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtirred with gree es, and expoſed to manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, my familie is conſtrained to ſeeke by a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie baniſhment among ſtrangers, the repoſe which it cannot finde with me: and as my expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces increaſe, my reuenewes doe diminiſh. But my conſcience doth ſo preſſe mee in this Cauſe, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ſhould bee abandoned of all and left alone (which I thinke will neuer be) I am reſolued to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it vntill the laſt drop of my blood, and to the laſt breath of my life: and though I ſhould goe begge my bread among ſtrange nations, God will giue mee the grace to iuſtifie vnto the world, that I neuer had other intent then to ſacrifice mine eſtate, my reſt, and my life, and to lay downe all my particular intereſts, for the deliuerance of the Church, without hauing any thought which ſhall tend to the reuolting from the obedience and fidelity whereunto nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth binde nice to the King my Soueraigne Lord.</p>
            <p>And in this caſe, (if that were all) I doe offer, that if the Church might bee re-eſtabliſhed in her firſt proſperity, voluntarily to exile my ſelfe from this Kingdome, and to paſſe the reſt of my life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſtrangers as a priuate man, and to renounce all honour and worldly aduantage, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue my ſelfe of the good and repoſe which I ſhould procure for others, to meditate by my ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:16624:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and to celebrate with continuall praiſes the fauour which God ſhould ſhew mee, to ſee yet once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine his poore people out of anguiſh and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and to haue gotten ſo great honour, to haue made my ſelfe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
